<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Eaglesky's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://eaglesky.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://eaglesky.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-27T14:56:34-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://eaglesky.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Yalun Qin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Color-Based Hand Gesture Recognition on Android]]></title>
    <link href="http://eaglesky.github.io/blog/2014/03/27/color-based-hand-gesture-recognition-on-android/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-27T14:40:57-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://eaglesky.github.io/blog/2014/03/27/color-based-hand-gesture-recognition-on-android</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is my course project for CS290I in UCSB. The aim is to detect and recognize
user-defined gestures using the camera of Android phone. I developed a simple
demo that let user call other applications using gestures to show the real time
performance.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>

<p>Nowadays mobile phones have been the most widely used and must-have electronic
gadgets. In recent years, the way how users interact with mobile phones has
evolved from QWERTY keyboards to touch screens. As is predicted by many people,
touch-free technologies like hand gesture recognition could probably be the
next user interface for mobile phones. This new interface gives a whole new way
to users for interacting with their phones, and in some scenarios can make
interaction easier than other ways. One possible situation is controlling the
play of music in the phone remotely. This can be achieved by using gesture
recognition as long as the hand is in the view of the camera. Another situation
is interacting with the phone when using the touch screen is not desirable. For
example, when the user is eating, his hands are probably dirty and greasy. It
will be much better and safer for the screen if the user can still use the
phone without touching it.</p>

<p>My project aims to detect hand gestures using the camera of Android phone and
recognize them using SVM classifier. Note that I only consider the static
gestures, which essentially are hand postures. The app I developed also maps
those gestures to some other pre-installed applications on the phone, enabling
the user to launch any of them by doing the corresponding gesture.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My First Blog Post]]></title>
    <link href="http://eaglesky.github.io/blog/2014/03/25/my-first-blog-post/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-25T14:03:18-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://eaglesky.github.io/blog/2014/03/25/my-first-blog-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="this-is-my-first-blog-post-using-octopress-also-the-first-time-to-write-a-post-using-markdown">This is my first blog post using Octopress. Also the first time to write a post using Markdown.</h2>

<p>Just for test.</p>

<h3 id="just-for-test">Just for test!</h3>

<!-- more -->

<h3 id="hope-youll-like-my-articles">Hope you’ll like my articles!</h3>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
